<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en, de"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en, de" /><updated>2025-05-05T16:20:58+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Verschiedenste Ideen, Buchrezensionen und Informationen.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Meta Benes ‘Philosophieren mit Tieren’</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/Philosophieren-mit-Tieren/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Meta Benes ‘Philosophieren mit Tieren’" /><published>2025-04-13T12:26:07+02:00</published><updated>2025-04-13T12:26:07+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/Philosophieren%20mit%20Tieren</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/Philosophieren-mit-Tieren/"><![CDATA[<p>Der Comic ‘Philosophieren mit Tieren’ von Meta Bene, erschienen 2024 bei Lappan, ist das Thema dieses Posts.</p>

<h2 id="das-buch">Das Buch</h2>

<p>In diesem Comic wird anhand des Gedankens, dass Tiere philosophieren können, ein humorvoller Spaziergang durch die Philosophie unternommen. In jedes Kapitel wird mit einem kurzen Text eingeführt, der dann mit minimalistischen, aussagekräftigen Illustrationen untermalt wird.</p>

<p>Unter der EAN 9783830336730 kann es in lokalen Buchläden bestellt werden.</p>

<h2 id="die-wirkung">Die Wirkung</h2>

<p>Die Tiere und ihre Gedanken und Aussagen bringen Lesende zum Lachen und regen zur Verwendung des eigenen Verstandes an. Anspielungen und Zitate menschlicher Philosophen können spielerisch erraten und in den Anmerkungen und Verweisen hinten im Buch überprüft werden.</p>

<p>Der ernste, aber spielerische Umgang mit Philosophie eröffnet die Möglichkeit, selber auch ein bisschen zu philosophieren.</p>

<h2 id="das-fazit">Das Fazit</h2>

<p>Ein Buch, das durch wiederholtes Lesen besser wird, weil die kurzen Darstellungen dazu einladen, die Entwicklung des eigenen Denkens zu beobachten.</p>

<p>Es ist sowohl ein guter Einstieg in die Philosophie als auch Anregung zu tiefergehenden Betrachtungen und nimmt sich selbst nicht zu ernst, das Thema aber schon.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><category term="deutsch" /><category term="Comic" /><category term="Philosophie" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[EAN 9783830336730]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Charlie Mackery’s ‘The Boy, the Mole, the Fox and the Horse. The Animated Story’</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/Boy-Mole-Fox-Horse/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Charlie Mackery’s ‘The Boy, the Mole, the Fox and the Horse. The Animated Story’" /><published>2025-04-11T11:06:04+02:00</published><updated>2025-04-11T11:06:04+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/Boy%20Mole%20Fox%20Horse</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/Boy-Mole-Fox-Horse/"><![CDATA[<p>The book ‘The Boy, the Mole, the Fox and the Horse. The Animated Story’ by Charlie Mackery, published in 2022 by Ebury Press, is the subject of this post.</p>

<h2 id="the-book">The book</h2>

<p>This book is the book of the film of the book - it uses the animations that were created when making the original book into a film and thus has a different preface explaining this story. Readers are greeted with beautiful writing and the statement of the author that the reader is hopefully ok, where ever they are. 
When you are reading the book the first time, I would recommend skipping this part and only reading it after finishing the book, because it already introduces the characters.</p>

<p>The pictures and the writing are very pretty and the story unfolds in a nice pace, while the open pages leave plenty of room for one’s own thoughts and emotions.</p>

<p>It can be ordered with the EAN 9781529197686 in local bookshops.</p>

<h2 id="the-impact">The impact</h2>

<p>More than telling a straight story this book is about how we treat each other and about how we view ourselves. It shows compassion and gentleness and the value of friendships and love and does that well.</p>

<h2 id="the-conclusion">The conclusion</h2>

<p>If you are looking for a book that explains everything and leaves no open spaces, this book is not the one for you.</p>

<p>If you want to be inspired and think about what is important to you in life, admire pretty pictures and a lovely font as well as see characters treat each other with kindness, empathy and acceptance, maybe give it a read.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><category term="english" /><category term="illustration" /><category term="heartwarming" /><category term="book" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[EAN 9781529197686]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ai Venturas ‘Japanische Backkunst’</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/Japanische-Backkunst/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ai Venturas ‘Japanische Backkunst’" /><published>2025-03-11T00:11:02+01:00</published><updated>2025-03-11T00:11:02+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/Japanische%20Backkunst</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/Japanische-Backkunst/"><![CDATA[<p>Das Buch ‘Japanische Backkunst. 45 süße Rezepte von Montblanc bis Mochi’, auf Deutsch erschienen 2023 im Christian Verlag, ist das Thema dieses Posts.</p>

<h2 id="das-buch">Das Buch</h2>

<p>Die Autorin beschreibt zunächst kurz ihre eigene Geschichte und die Geschichte der Backkunst in Japan. Danach werden Überblicke über Zutaten und Materialien gegeben woraufhin die Rezepte folgen. Am Ende des Buchs werden einzelne Techniken detailliert und mit Bildern verdeutlicht dargestellt, die das Backen erleichtern.</p>

<p>Unter der EAN 9783959618113 kann es in lokalen Buchläden bestellt werden.</p>

<h2 id="die-wirkung">Die Wirkung</h2>

<p>Mich erfreut an diesem Buch vor allem die Präzision, mit der die Rezepte und Zutatenlisten beschrieben werden. Grammangaben bei Eier kannte ich sonst primär vom Macaronbacken und finde es hier wie dort sehr hilfreich, die genauen Mengen zu kennen.</p>

<p>Dieses Buch begleitet mich nun schon länger und die letzten beiden Jahre waren meine Geburtstagskuchen immer aus diesem Buch - köstlich!</p>

<h2 id="das-fazit">Das Fazit</h2>

<p>Dieses Backbuch gibt nicht nur Hintergrundinformationen zu japanischer Backkunst und Backtechniken, sondern auch präzise Rezepte, mit deren Hilfe das Gebäck gut gelingen kann.</p>

<p>Die Rezepte sind aufwändiger als eine Limonadentorte, überzeugen aber durch Geschmack und Mundgefühl und das Backen selbst ist durch die klaren Anweisungen eine wahre Freude.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><category term="deutsch" /><category term="Backbuch" /><category term="backen" /><category term="Rezepte" /><category term="japanisch" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[EAN 9783959618113]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Terry Pratchett’s ‘Witches Abroad’</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/Witches-Abroad/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Terry Pratchett’s ‘Witches Abroad’" /><published>2025-02-11T08:32:03+01:00</published><updated>2025-02-11T08:32:03+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/Witches%20Abroad</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/Witches-Abroad/"><![CDATA[<p>The discworld novel ‘Witches Abroad’ written by Terry Pratchett and published in 1992 with Corgi Books, first published in 1991 with Gollancz, is the subject of this post.</p>

<h2 id="the-book">The book</h2>

<p>This book returns to the discworld witches and follows them on their journey to foreign lands, where they have to fight the power of stories.</p>

<p>This edition (EAN 9780552134651) might be harder to order, but there are newer editions as well as the translated versions ready to be ordered in local bookshops. It might also be possible to find this second hand in good condition, as the discworld books have many fans.</p>

<h2 id="the-impact">The impact</h2>

<p>This novel can be enjoyed on different levels as is the case with all discworld books. In this one we don’t only have the plain level of the witches adventures and the level that relates to our world, but additionally the meta level of a story about stories and their power. 
The beautiful thing is that it can be enjoyed on either of these levels alone or combining all of them, making it a tempting read for many people. 
The characters are amazing, the footnotes hilarious and the book had me laugh tears several times.</p>

<h2 id="the-conclusion">The conclusion</h2>

<p>Years after reading it the first time (in 2014) I read the novel again and enjoyed it tremendously. A bit of discworld knowledge probably helps in not getting overwhelmed by all the details, but it can also serve as an entry point into some of the leading forces on the discworld. Highly recommended.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><category term="english" /><category term="discworld" /><category term="fantasy" /><category term="clever" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[EAN 9780552134651]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Marc-Uwe Klings ‘Die Känguru-Tetralogie’</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/K%C3%A4nguru-Tetralogie/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Marc-Uwe Klings ‘Die Känguru-Tetralogie’" /><published>2025-01-11T12:32:03+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-11T12:32:03+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/K%C3%A4nguru%20Tetralogie</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/K%C3%A4nguru-Tetralogie/"><![CDATA[<p>Der Schuber mit vier Büchern von Marc-Uwe Kling, der in dieser Form 2020 bei Ullstein erschienen ist, ist das Thema dieses Posts.</p>

<h2 id="die-bücher">Die Bücher</h2>

<p>Enthalten sind ‘Die Känguru-Chroniken’, ‘Das Känguru-Manifest’, ‘Die Känguru-Offenbarung’ sowie ‘Die Känguru-Apokryphen’, die alle schon vorher als Einzelbände erschienen waren.</p>

<p>Erzählt wird die sehr witzige Geschichte des Protagonisten, der zu Beginn des ersten Buches mit einem Känguru zusammenzieht. 
Es wird diskutiert, philosophiert und die Welt verbessert.</p>

<p>Unter der EAN 9783548061610 kann der Schuber in lokalen Buchläden bestellt werden.</p>

<p>Empfehlenswert sind auch die Hörbücher, die der Autor selbst vorliest.</p>

<h2 id="die-wirkung">Die Wirkung</h2>

<p>Diese Bücher bieten spannende und lustige Unterhaltung, erlauben Lesenden aber auch, sich in philosophische und politische Debatten zu denken und tragen so dazu bei, sich aus der selbstverschuldeten Unmündigkeit zu befreien.</p>

<p>Das Zusammenleben des Protagonisten mit dem Känguru ist voller Skurrilität, Gesellschaftskritik und Lachen.</p>

<h2 id="das-fazit">Das Fazit</h2>

<p>Diese Bücher sind für mich so lesenswert, weil es in ihnen gelingt, ernste Themen humorvoll zu beleuchten und dadurch zum Denken anregen. Sie sagen für mich: Sapere aude!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><category term="deutsch" /><category term="Känguru" /><category term="witzig" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[EAN 9783548061610]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Emma Southons ‘Eine Geschichte des Römischen Reiches in 21 Frauen’</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/Geschichte-des-r%C3%B6mischen-Reiches/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Emma Southons ‘Eine Geschichte des Römischen Reiches in 21 Frauen’" /><published>2024-12-17T22:13:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-12-17T22:13:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/Geschichte%20des%20r%C3%B6mischen%20Reiches</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/Geschichte-des-r%C3%B6mischen-Reiches/"><![CDATA[<p>Das Buch ‘Eine Geschichte des Römischen Reiches in 21 Frauen’ von Emma Southon, auf Deutsch erschienen 2024 bei Aufbau, ist das Thema dieses Posts.</p>

<h2 id="das-buch">Das Buch</h2>

<p>Das im Englischen unter dem Titel ‘A History of the Roman Empire in 21 Women’ erschienene Buch befasst sich genau mit dem, was der Titel aussagt:</p>

<p>Es beleuchtet die Leben von Frauen, die im Zusammenhang mit dem Römischen Reich stehen, und bietet so eine ungewohnte Perspektive auf römische Geschichte.</p>

<p>Unter der EAN 9783351042387 kann es in lokalen Buchläden bestellt werden.</p>

<h2 id="die-wirkung">Die Wirkung</h2>

<p>Das Buch erlaubt es, die in der Geschichtsschreibung übliche Perspektive auf Männer zu verlassen.
Dadurch wird es ermöglicht, mehr vom alltäglichen Leben von historischen Frauen zu erfahren, was wiederum einen neuen Blick auf die Gegenwart zulässt.</p>

<p>Durch dieses Buch wird in besonderer Weise verdeutlicht, dass Frauen schon immer Teil des (öffentlichen) Lebens waren und Einfluss nahmen.</p>

<h2 id="das-fazit">Das Fazit</h2>
<p>Dieses Buch versorgt die Lesenden mit vielen Informationen, die noch lange nachhallen.</p>

<p>So werden ungehörte Ergänzungen und ungesehene Perspektiven mit dem aus der Schulzeit vorhandenen Wissen kombiniert und fördern so ein runderes, realistischeres Bild des Römischen Reichs.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><category term="deutsch" /><category term="Geschichte" /><category term="Sachbuch" /><category term="informativ" /><category term="Rom" /><category term="Frauen" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[EAN 9783351042387]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Travis Baldree’s ‘Legends &amp;amp; Lattes’</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/Legends-and-Lattes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Travis Baldree’s ‘Legends &amp;amp; Lattes’" /><published>2024-11-17T18:37:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-11-17T18:37:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/Legends-and-Lattes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/Legends-and-Lattes/"><![CDATA[<p>The cosy fantasy novel ‘Legends &amp; Lattes’ written by Travis Baldree and published in 2022 with Tor is the subject of this post.</p>

<h2 id="the-book">The book</h2>

<p>The book describes the path of orc Viv to owning her own quaint coffee shop, while she tries to leave fighting and trouble behind her for a more peaceful life. On the way the reader meets exciting and lovable characters and gets to know Viv and her inner struggles as well as her solutions to them better.</p>

<p>It can be ordered with the EAN 9781035007325 in local bookshops.</p>

<h2 id="the-impact">The impact</h2>

<p>This novel is sweet and calm and cosy as well as having exciting and peculiar and whimsical moments. The desire to live a slower life filled with peace and surrounded by warm-hearted people shines through the whole book and makes the reader take a breath and consider what might be more important than being the strongest swordswoman or the mightiest warrior.</p>

<h2 id="the-conclusion">The conclusion</h2>

<p>Perfect for a cosy winter read, cuddled up under the blankets with a lovely cup of hot drink of choice – and trying to replicate the recipes afterwards.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><category term="english" /><category term="love" /><category term="fantasy" /><category term="cosy" /><category term="coffee" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[EAN 9781035007325]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bolu Babalola’s ‘Love in Colour’</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/Love-in-colour/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bolu Babalola’s ‘Love in Colour’" /><published>2024-10-17T19:37:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-10-17T19:37:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/Love-in-colour</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/Love-in-colour/"><![CDATA[<p>The collection of stories in Bolu Babalola’s book ‘Love in Colour’ published in 2020 by Headline Publishing Group are the subject of this post.</p>

<h2 id="the-book">The book</h2>

<p>The book contains multiple stories that offer a fresh view on old myths engaging with the subject of love. It starts with ten stories referring to old myths, followed by three new tales. The length of the stories varies, but most of them are around twenty pages long, which makes it very easy to pick the book up again and jump right in after life interfering with the read.</p>

<p>It can be ordered with the EAN 9781472268884 in local bookshops.</p>

<h2 id="the-impact">The impact</h2>

<p>This book can make the reader reconsider their own perspectives, be a joyful pastime or promote own research into the myths and figures that are mentioned. It shows that love doesn’t have to mean heartache and drama (although it might mean that as well) and that the definition of love very much depends on the individuals being in love with each other. Some things should obviously always be counted into the mix, consent, benevolence and communication being fundamental, but the details can vary from lovers to lovers.</p>

<p>To quote the author: “Love enriches the world we inhabit.”</p>

<h2 id="the-conclusion">The conclusion</h2>

<p>Highly recommended read, I especially love the strong female characters.</p>

<p>The language is electrifying, the characters are well rounded and the plots exciting.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><category term="shortstories" /><category term="english" /><category term="love" /><category term="tales" /><category term="myths" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[EAN 9781472268884]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tomoko Kakita’s ‘Furoshiki and the Japanese Art of Gift Wrapping’</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/Furoshiki/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tomoko Kakita’s ‘Furoshiki and the Japanese Art of Gift Wrapping’" /><published>2024-10-16T00:47:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-10-16T00:47:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/Furoshiki</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/Furoshiki/"><![CDATA[<p>The instructive book ‘Furoshiki and the Japanese Art of Gift Wrapping’ from Tokoko Kakita released in 2021 by Laurence King Publishing is the subject of this post.</p>

<h2 id="the-book">The book</h2>

<p>The book explains different ways to wrap gifts and other items in pretty fabric. It features a short introductory explanation of the history and usage of Furoshiki and thirty illustrated wrapping styles.</p>

<p>It can be ordered with the EAN 9781913947651 in local bookshops.</p>

<h2 id="the-impact">The impact</h2>

<p>The book inspires to (re-)use fabric instead of paper, thus reducing waste and improving sustainability. It is interesting to learn about other gift wrapping options and the history of Furoshiki, but the most exciting part is using the wrapping styles to lovingly wrap gifts or bento boxes or to just miraculously have an emergency bag.</p>

<h2 id="the-conclusion">The conclusion</h2>

<p>The fabrics that are used to wrap gifts can be gifted back and forth for years, adding to a gifting tradition and creating a bit of nostalgia at the same time. The book can be a lovely gift itself, but using it oneself is a lot of fun as well.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><category term="gift" /><category term="english" /><category term="japanese" /><category term="instructions" /><category term="creative" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[EAN 9781913947651]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">kriegundfreitags ‘Psyche, du kleiner Schlingel’</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/Psyche/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="kriegundfreitags ‘Psyche, du kleiner Schlingel’" /><published>2024-10-03T14:07:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-10-03T14:07:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/Psyche</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/Psyche/"><![CDATA[<p>Das Buch ‘Psyche, du kleiner Schlingel’, erschienen 2021 beim Lappan Verlag, ist das Thema dieses Posts.</p>

<h2 id="das-buch">Das Buch</h2>

<p>In ‘Psyche, du kleiner Schlingel’ zeigt kriegundfreitag (Tobias Vogel) mit der Hilfe von charmanten Zeichnungen Einblicke in das menschliche Innenleben.</p>

<p>Unter der EAN 9783830336136 kann es in lokalen Buchläden bestellt werden.</p>

<h2 id="die-wirkung">Die Wirkung</h2>
<p>Die Comics bringen Lesende zum Lachen, lassen innehalten und regen zum Nachdenken an. Während manche der Comics pure Witzigkeit im ursprünglichen Sinn darstellen, zeigen andere einen warmherzigen Blick auf Melancholie und Weltschmerz. Lesende werden abgeholt, unabhängig von ihrer aktuellen Gefühlslage, und fühlen sich im besten Fall mit diesem Buch weniger allein.</p>

<h2 id="das-fazit">Das Fazit</h2>
<p>Die Comics von @kriegundfreitag sind tiefgründig und feinfühlig, sensibel und liebevoll. Auch wenn schwierige Themen angesprochen werden, ist stets ein Wohlwollen dem Menschen gegenüber zu erkennen. Gut als Geschenk für sich selbst oder andere.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><category term="Philosophie" /><category term="deutsch" /><category term="Comic" /><category term="Gesellschaftskritik" /><category term="Psyche" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[EAN 9783830336136]]></summary></entry></feed>